冰河世纪
为什么不管这叫“大寒”或者“冷冻时代”
Why not call itthe Big Chill or the Nippy era?
我是说我们怎么知道这是“冰川时代”？
I'm just saying,how do we know it's an ice age?
因为四周全是冰！
Because of all the ice.
就连说话也冷冰冰的
Well, things just got a little chillier.
救命
Help. Help.
来吧，孩子，我们走，大伙儿都在走呢！
Come on, kids, let's go. The traffic's moving.
可是，可是，可是，爸爸
But, but, but, Dad.
别说“可是”还轮不到你绝种呢
No buts. You can play extinction later.
噢，OK，走吧，伙计们
OK. Come on, guys.
我说……艾迪在哪儿？
So, where's Eddie?
啊，他说他马上就要出现一个“进化上的突破”了
He said he was on the vergeof an evolutionary breakthrough.
是吗？
Really?
噢，我飞了！
I'm flying.
好一个突破
Some breakthrough.
小心！你走错方向了！
- Look out.- You're going the wrong way.
你这毛象疯子！
Crazy mammoth.
嘿！你就帮个忙吧！别挡着道妨碍交通！
Do the world a favor.Move your issues off the road.
如果我也是短鼻子我就不会那么抢眼了，老弟！
If my trunk was that small,I wouldn't draw attention to myself, pal.
别臭我了我们……都挪了一整天了
Give me a break.We've been waddling all day.
那就接着走吧，随大流吧
Go ahead. Follow the crowd.
你们走了就清静了
It'll be quieter when you're gone.
走吧，他要冻死就随他去
Come on. If he wants tofreeze to death, let him.
嘿，嘿，我醒了，醒了
I'm up. I'm up.
大家都快起来吧！呃？扎克？马歇尔？
Rise and shine, everybody.Huh? Zak? Marshall?
伯蒂？“真菌”叔叔？
Bertie? Uncle Fungus?
大家都去哪儿了？来吧，伙计们，我们该迁…该迁…迁徙了
Where is everybody? Come on, guys,we're gonna miss the migration.
扔下我就走了他们每年…都这么干！
They left without me.They do this every year.
为什么？谁都不爱我了吗？
Why? Doesn't anyone love me?
难道谁都不关心我这可怜的树懒希德了吗？
Isn't there anyone who cares about Sid the Sloth?
好吧，那我就自己走
All right, I'll just go by myself.
噢，恶心！
Sick.
嘿，巨无霸！别随地大小便！
Wide body, curb it next time.
噢，天，噢，唉唷！噢！
Oh, jeez. Yuck.
真不敢相信，新鲜绿叶菜弗兰克，你在哪儿找到的？
I can't believe it. Fresh wild greens.Frank, where did you ever...?
好了，快吃吧是蒲公英？
- Go ahead. Dig in.- A dandelion.
还以为都被冻死了就剩下这一棵
- I thought the frost wiped 'em all out.- All but one.
唷,唷,这实在让我太我要咬他的…啊
It makes me so... I wanna... Yuck.
我呸！今天我算是倒霉透了我的意思你应该懂吧？
This has definitely not been my day.You know what I'm saying, buddy?
简直一团糟，你们犀牛的脑袋实在是小，你们知道吗？
What a mess. You rhinos have tiny brains. Did you know that?
这是事实，我没有恶意也许我的话你们根本不懂
It's just a fact. No offense. You probably didn't even know what I'm talking about.
呵呵呵呵，噢，美味呀！
Yummo.
是蒲公英呀！一定是最后一棵了
A dandelion. Must bethe last one of the season.
卡尔？冷静，弗兰克
- Carl.- Easy, Frank.
他糟蹋了我们的色拉
He ruined our salad.
呃，呃，噢，噢，是我错了
My mistake. That was my mistake. Let me...
伙计们，我错了，我赔我赔呃，这是什么？
No, no, seriously, let me take care of this. What is this?
是松果啊！噢，老天，我最爱吃了！
Pine cones. Oh, my goodness.They're my favorite.
唔，味道好极了嗷，这真…呃，真好吃
Delicious. That's good eating.
你们可不能让我独享了你们也吃点
But don't let me hog them all up.Here, you have some.
味道不错吧？祝你们胃口好
Tasty, isn't it? "BON APPITITE(法语)."
上吗？
Now?
上
假装我不在我是想全速把他撞倒
- Just pretend that I'm not here.- I wanted to hit him at full speed.
别急，我们“玩玩”他.别让他们刺穿我，拜托了，我想活命
- That's OK. We'll have some fun with him.- Don't let them impale me. I wanna live.
你走开！行了，你就别撒泼了
- Get off me.- Come on, you're making a scene.
我们只要把那毛小子戳爆然后就走
We'll just take our furry pinata and go.
嘿，小子，逃得了今天也逃不过明天
If it's not them today,it's someone else tomorrow.
反正我今天不想死，OK？
Well, I'd rather it not be today. OK?
听着，我们戳断你的脖子你不会痛苦的，怎么样？
We'll break your neck so you don't feel a thing.
等一下，你们犀牛应该是食草动物吧？
Wait a minute. I thought rhinos were vegetarians.
真精辟！闭嘴！
- An excellent point.- Shut up.
谁说我们把他杀了之后要吃他？
Who says we're gonna eat him after we kill him?
我不喜欢以杀为乐的动物
I don't like animals that kill for pleasure.
谁爱听…就跟谁说吧恰好我就爱听
- Save it for a mammal that cares.- I'm a mammal that cares.
好吧,如果你们俩有谁过得了前面这个坑，树懒就归你们
OK, if either of you make it across that sinkhole in front of ya, you get the sloth.
没错，孬种往前跨一步就死定了！
That's right, you losers.You take one step and you're dead.
你在吓唬他们？对，这“坑”不会沉
- You were bluffing, huh?- Yeah. Yeah, that was a bluff.
收拾他！
Get him.
是蒲公英？
A dandelion?
哇！我们胜利了！
We did it.
你的眼睛真美！快滚下我的脸！
- You have beautiful eyes.- Get off my face.
噢，你和我，我俩配合默契不如结伴一起去南方吧
Whoa, we make a great team.What do you say we head south together?
好啊，耶！嘿，跳到我背上来一路放轻松
Great. Jump on my backand relax the whole way.
哇噢，当真？
- Wow, really?- No.
等等，你不去南方？季节的变换，迁徙的本能
Wait, aren't you going south?The change of seasons, migration instincts.
这些挺耳熟吧？不，再见了
- Any of this a-ringing a bell?- I guess not. Bye.
好吧，多谢帮忙我自己走吧
OK, then. Thanks for the help.I can take it from here.
嘿，你象只大号的鼬鼠有种等我们下来
You overgrown weasel.Wait till we get down there.
何必一窝蜂地去南方又热又挤的，没意思
That south thing is way overrated.The heat, the crowds - who needs it?
还是这样好，你和我两个单身汉在荒野中闲逛
Isn't this great? You and me,two bachelors knocking about in the wild.
不，你是想要保镖生怕自己被活吞了
No, you just want a bodyguard so you don't become somebody's side dish.
你这家伙还真够精明的
You're a very shrewd mammal.
那你带路吧先生，你叫…叫啥来着？
OK, lead the way, Mr Big...Didn't get the name.
曼福雷德曼福雷德？难听
- Manfred.- Manfred? Yuck.
不如叫“曼尼-忧郁的毛象”“曼尼-深沉的愁思者…曼尼…”
How about Manny the Moody Mammoth?Or Manny the Melancholy... Manny the...
别再跟着我
Stop following me.
好吧，好吧，你有心事听着，你就当我不在，我会闭嘴
OK, so you've got issues. You won'teven know I'm here. I'll just zip the lip.
噢，你快瞧啊那可爱的…小宝宝，迭戈
Look at the cute little baby, Diego.
把他拿来当早餐一定很美妙没有他怎么能算早餐？
- lsn't it nice he'll be joining us for breakfast?- It wouldn't be breakfast without him.
尤其因为他爸爸杀了我们一半的同胞，穿上我们的毛皮取暖
Especially since his daddy wiped out halfour pack and wears our skin to keep warm.
以牙还牙，你看怎么样？
An eye for an eye, don't you think?
让那人知道跟剑齿虎斗是什么下场
Let's show him what happens when he messes with sabers.
通知大伙儿，我们黎明进攻
Alert the troops. We attack at dawn.
迭戈，把那孩子带来，要活的
And, Diego, bring me that baby alive.
如果要好好享受报仇那最好是活吞
If I'm gonna enjoy my revenge,I want it to be fresh.
噢，累死我了
Phew. I'm wiped out.
你用这点过夜？嘿，你块头大，你有很多木头
- That's your shelter?- You're a big guy. You got a lotta wood.
我是小不点儿所以只要半根
- I'm a little guy.- You got half a stick.
可…有我的小木棍和我高度进化的脑子…我能生出…火！
But with my little stick and my highly evolved brain, I shall create fire.
了不起
Fascinating.
看看智慧是不是能战胜蛮力你瞧着吧
We'll see if brains triumph over brawn tonight. Now, won't we?
嘿，我看见火花了
Think I saw a spark.
呃，我能不能进来跟你一块挤一挤，曼尼老伙计？
Any chance I could squeeze in there with you, Manny, ol' pal?
呃，你还是去烦别的家伙吧
Isn't there someone else you can annoy?
朋友、亲戚或者毒蛇什么的
Friends? Family? Poisonous reptiles?
我全家丢下了我他们不管我…自己迁徙了
My family abandoned me.They just kinda migrated without me.
他们去年还要过分
You should see what they did last year.
他们很早醒来然后绑住我的手脚
They woke up early andtied my hands and feet
用田鼠塞住我的嘴并且把洞门堵上
and they gagged me with a field mouse,
他们走水路这样我就闻不出它们的气味
covered their tracks, went through water so I'd lose their scent,
反…反正…我也不需要他们
and... who needs 'em, anyway?
你怎么样？有家庭吗？
So what about you? You have family?
好吧，看来你累了我们天亮再谈
OK, you're tired. I see.We'll talk more in the morning.
曼福雷德！你挪过去点好吗？
Manfred? Manfred?Could you scooch over a drop?
噢，得了哪会这么快就睡着的！曼尼！
Come on. Nobody falls asleep that fast.
曼尼
Manny
迭戈来了，我们撤
There's Diego. Fall back.
小孩在哪儿？在瀑布那儿追丢了
- Where's the baby?- I lost it over the falls.
你追丢了？
You lost it?
我要那小孩，迭戈我能找到
- I want that baby, Diego.- I'll get it.
但愿如此不然的话被活吞的就是你
You'd better, unless you want to serve as a replacement.
我们去“半峰”山去那儿会合
We'll go up to Half Peak. Meet us there.
最好把他活着带来
It had better be alive.
能完成这任务吗？迭戈？
Can we trust you with that, Diego?
我们走！
Let's go.
她看见我肩上的那根毛就说如果你找别的女伴风流
She picked a hair off my shoulder and says,"lf you have an extra mating dance,
至少找一个毛的颜色相同的
at least pick a female with the same color pelt."
我想“完了”我要成她的盘中餐了
I thought "Whoa. She's gonna go praying mantis on me."
如果你有了配偶就该对她忠诚，你很幸运了
If you find a mate, you should be loyal.In your case, grateful.
你给我走开一辈子守着一个太蠢了
- Now get away from me.- I think mating for life is stupid.
那也太亏了我这“能干”的希德
There's plenty of Sid to go around.
曼尼？
Manny?
快瞧啊，他没事
Look at that. He's OK.
他妈妈不见了
She's gone.
你是不是忘了什么？
- Manny, are you forgetting something?- No.
可…可你刚救了他可上次救的那个我还没甩掉呢
- But you just saved him.- I'm trying to get rid of the last thing I saved.
你不能把他留在这儿
But you can't leave him here.
瞧，有烟他的那群人在山上
Look, there's smoke.That's his herd right up the hill.
我们把他送回去我跟你说白了吧，根本没有“我们”
- We should return him.- Let's get this straight. There is no "we."
从来就没有“我们”，其实没有我，这会我连“你”都没了
There never was a "we." In fact,without me, there wouldn't even be a "you."
只是去山上你给我仔细听好，我就是不去！
- Just up the hill.- Listen very carefully: I'm not going.
行啊，做你的混球，我会照顾他的噢，好，太好了
- Fine, be a jerk. I'll take care of him.- Yeah, that's good.
你连自己都照顾不了我倒要瞧瞧
You can't even take care of yourself.This, I gotta see.
我送你回去我们不需要那坏蛋毛象，对吗？
I'll return you. We don't need that meany-weeny mammoth, do we?
不需要他
No, we don't.
你真给大自然丢脸这你知道吗？
You're an embarrassment to nature.Do you know that?
小菜一碟，我行，我行
Piece of cake. I'm fine, I'm fine.
我会送命的
I'm gonna die.
曼尼
Manny.
唔…那小东西是我的不对，这小东西是我们的
- That pink thing is mine.- No. Actually, that pink thing belongs to us.
“我们”？你们“小俩口”真是“绝配”啊
"Us"? You two are a bit of an odd couple.
没有“我们”！
There is no "us."
懂了自己生不出，所以领养一个
I see. Can't have one of your own,so you want to adopt.
对不起，搅了你吃“点心”可我们得走了
Look, I'm sorry to interrupt your snack, but we gotta go.
吃小孩？得了，我是要把他送回去
The baby? Please.I was returning him to his herd.
噢，行呀，真有你的，“龅牙”
Oh, yeah. Nice try, bucktooth.
你说我在撒谎？我没这么说
- Calling me a liar?- I didn't say that.
你就是这么想的
You were thinking it.
我不喜欢这家伙他猜透我心思
I don't like this cat. He reads minds.
我叫迭戈，朋友曼福雷德，我不是你朋友
- Name's Diego, friend.- Manfred, and I'm not your friend.
好吧，别白费劲找人类了他们今天早上走了
Fine, Manfred. If you're looking for the humans, you're wasting your time. They left.
谢谢你的建议，现在滚吧
Thanks for the advice. Now beat it.
好吧，我帮你把他送回去但你得保证完事后不缠着我
I'll help you bring it to its herd,but leave me alone after that.
好吧，说定了，你哪儿不对劲？全都因为你
- OK. OK, deal. What's your problem?- You are my problem.
你是因为太紧张，所以你吃那么多注意减肥就不会胖了
I think you're stressed, so you eat too much.It's hard to get fat on a vegan diet.
我不胖，是因为这毛皮让我显得…臃肿
I'm not fat. It's all this fur.It makes me look poofy.
好吧，那你有“肥毛”如果有烦心事想说，我听着
All right, you have fat hair.But when you're ready to talk, I'm here.
你干嘛？把他放在岩脊上
What are you doing? Just drop it on the ledge.
应该保证他们能看见好主意
- We should make sure they found him.- Good idea.
等等，等等
No, no. Wait, wait, wait, wait.
啊！别…刺我！
Don't spear me.
呃…这下麻烦了怎么了？
- This is a problem.- Now what?
噢，这下可好
That's perfect.
我说过他们都走了瞧谁来了
- I told you they were gone.- Look who it is.
找不到弱小的动物让你开膛破肚了？
Don't you have some poor animal to disembowel?
噢，他们走不远的，往这边走了或，或或，或…这边
They couldn't be far. I mean,they went this way, or this way?
你不太懂追踪，对吗？
You don't know much about tracking, do you?
嘿，我是树懒，看见树就吃叶子，我管这叫“追踪”
I'm a sloth. I see a tree,eat a leaf. That's my tracking.
他们没走多久
You didn't miss them by much.
这还青着两小时前，往北去了
It's still green.They headed north two hours ago.
你们不用这么折腾
You don't need this aggravation.
把孩子给我我能比你们更快找到人类
Give me the baby. I can track humans down a lot faster than you.
你真是个热情相助的好公民
And you're just a good citizen helping out?
我知道人类去哪儿了“冰川道”
- I just know where the humans are going.- Glacier Pass.
谁都知道他们在另一边有个居住地
Everybody knows they havea settlement on the other side.
如果你们不懂追踪，在大雪封住通道前就找不到他们
Unless you know how to track, you'll never reach them before snow closes the pass.
大雪封路可能…是明天
Which should be, like, tomorrow.
所以，要么把孩子给我要么在暴风雪中迷路，你们选择吧
So, you can give that baby to me,or go get lost in a blizzard. It's your choice.
抱着你的心肝宝贝我们把他还给人类
Here's your little bundle of joy.We're returning it to the humans.
大坏蛋“老虎叔叔”被我们扔下不管了，可怜的“老虎叔叔”
The big, bad tigey-wigey gets left behind.Poor tigey-wigey.
希德，“老虎叔叔”负责带路
Sid, tigey-wigey is gonna lead the way.
呃，呃，曼尼我能不能跟你谈谈？
Manny, can I talk to you for a second?
不，我们早点找到人类，我就能早点摆脱这流口水的臭家伙
No. The sooner we find the humans,the sooner I get rid of Mr Stinky Drool-Face,
还有这孩子
and the baby, too.
“金刚巨象”不会时刻保护你的
You won't always have Jumbo around to protect you.
哪天你没了保护，我劝你最好小心点，因为我会偷袭你
And when that day comes, I suggest you watch your back, cos I'll be chewing on it.
嘿，“追踪大师”，到前面来，好让我看见！
Nier-tracker. Up front, where I can see you
救救我
Help me.
噢，你别让他再哭了我再也受不了了！
You gotta make it stop.I can't take it anymore.
没他这么会闹的我也吃过他不停扭动
- I've eaten things that complained less.- He won't stop squirming.
小心他的头！你把他放下！
- Watch its head.- Put it down.
唏，“抱起来，放下他”
Jeez, "pick him up, put him down..."
他的鼻子是干的那他一定是生病了
- lts nose is dry.- That means something's wrong with it.
谁来给他舔舔，以防万一我来吧
- Someone should lick it. Just in case.- I'll do it.
嘿，他包着尿布呢！怎么？
- He's wearing one of those baby thingies.- So?
如果他拉屎，就拉尿布里
So if he poops, where does it go?
人类真是恶心好吧你，检查大便
- Humans are disgusting.- OK, you. Check for poop.
嘿，凭什么让我检查？因为是你要送他回去
- Why am I the poop-checker?- Returning him was your idea,
因为你无足轻重因为你不检查我就揍你
you're small and insignificant,and I'll pummel you if you don't.
还有吗？快！希德！
- Why else?- Now, Sid.
唷！哎哟我的妈呀好了，小心，小心，过来了
I mean, my goodness.Look out. Coming through.
嘿，小心！别拿它晃来晃去的！
- Watch out.- Stop waving that thing around.
呜，我要滑倒了，啊
I'm gonna slip.
是干净的，你上当了
It's clean. Got ya!
别胡闹行吗？
Will you cut it out?
嘿，再来，他喜欢
Do that again. He likes it.
我也觉得爽多了
It's making me feel better too.
给，你来抱
Here, you hold it.
行了，让他脸朝我
Turn him towards me.
宝宝在哪儿？
Where is the baby?
他在这儿！
There he is.
宝宝在哪儿？
Where is the baby?
他在这儿！
There he is.
行了！你吓坏他了！
Stop it. You're scaring him.
他一定是饿了该吃奶了
- I bet he's hungry.- How about some milk?
噢，我爱吃奶！不是你吃！是孩子吃！
- I'd love some.- Not you. The baby.
我可没有奶水给他喝，伙计
I aingt exactly lactating right now, pal.
你这食物链底层的没资格顶嘴
- You're a little low on the food chain to...
够了！够了！够了！
Enough, enough, enough.
有吃的！
Food.
我不知道，可我听说
I don't know, but I've been told
世界末日会很冷
End of the world be mighty cold
为冰川时代作准备！
Prepare for the lce age!
保护渡渡鸟的生活方式！
Protect the dodo way of life!
渡渡鸟的生存能力胜过其他动物！
Survival separates the dodos from the beasts!
保护渡渡鸟的生活方式！
Protect the dodo way of life!
为冰川时代做准备！
Prepare for the lce age!
冰川时代？我听说过这些疯子
- lce age?- I've heard of these crackpots.
有闯入者！闯入者！别掉进去
- lntruders.- Now, don't fall in.
掉进去，就一定会…有闯…闯入者，闯入…哇！
- If you do, you will definitely...- lntruders. Intruder...
被烫死了
..burn and die.
能把西瓜给我们吗？小家伙饿坏了，他…
Can we have our melon back?Junior's hungry and...
不行！这是我们为冰川时代存下的储备！
No way. This is our privatestockpile for the lce age.
到那个时候我们就要在地下住好几十亿年呢！
Subarctic temperatures will force us underground for a billion years.
只存三只西瓜？
So you got three melons?
如果你们事先不好好作准备那就死定了！
If you weren't smart enough to plan ahead, then doom on you.
死定了，死定了，死定了
Doom on you. Doom on you. Doom on you.
别过来
- Get away from me.- Doom on you.
哦，不，不
Oh, no. No.
夺回那西瓜！跆…跆拳道准备！进攻！
Retrieve the melon.Tae kwon dodos, attack.
西瓜！
- The melon.- The melon, the melon, the melon...
最后一个“女同胞”也完了
There goes our last female.
抢到了，抢到了，抢到了又没了！
- Got it, got it, got it.- Don't got it.
最后的西瓜
The last melon.
啊，希德！还得再找吃的了！
Sid. Now we gotta find more food.
再往右一点！
Right, more to the right. Right, right, right.
嘿，晚餐还有表演看不，左，左，左，不
- Look at that. Dinner and a show.- Left, left, left.
现在该找份象样的大餐犒劳胜利英雄了
Now to find a meal befitting a conquering hero.
是什么？敌人？来吧，想跟我干一架吗？
What ho? A foe? Come on,come on. You want a piece of me?
这战利品值得我为它好好…
Spoils worthy of such a noble...
该睡了，小鬼
Bedtime, squirt.
噢，凯旋归来了
The triumphant return.
呃？噢，那是
Huh? Oh, that.
呃…我吃饱了该亲亲这个小朋友说晚安了
I'm so full. How about a good-night kiss for your big buddy, Sid?
嘘，他睡着了我是在跟你说
- He's asleep.- I was talking to you.
算了，我自己睡吧
Fine, I'll talk myself in.
好了，晚安
All right, good night.
别吵了行吗？
Will you stop it?
好吧，好吧，我是想放松
All right, all right. I was trying to relax.
哎唷
Oy.
搞什么朝我上呀，看我不把你撕碎
- What the...?- Slice me. It'll be the last thing you ever do.
我在办事，你这饭桶很郁闷吧，迭戈？
- I'm working here, you waste of fur.- Frustrated, Diego?
找个小不点婴儿对你来说太难了？
Tracking down helpless infants too difficult for you?
你们俩来这干嘛？索托已经等得不耐烦了
- What are you two doing here?- Soto's getting tired of waiting.
他说要么带着小孩回来要么就别回来了！
Yeah, he said "Come back with the baby,or don't come back at all."
替我捎个信给索托
I have a message for Soto.
告诉他…我会带孩子来
Tell him I'm bringing the baby.
再告诉他，我还带…
And tell him I'm bringing...
一头毛象
a mammoth.
毛象？毛象从不单独行动
- A mammoth?- Mammoths never travel alone.
可这头是例外我要带他去“半峰”山
This one does,and I'm leading him to Half Peak.
呜，瞧他那身肉，杀了他！
Look at all that meat. Let's get him.
还不行！得叫大伙儿一起上才能摆平他
Not yet. We'll need the whole packto bring this mammoth down.
让大家快准备
Get everyone ready.
快去！
Now.
孩子在哪儿？你把他丢了？
- Where's the baby?- You lost it?
希德
Sid.
呜，他可真丑他可真是太可爱了
It's so ugly. Positively adorable.
你好，小心肝你好，没毛的小家伙
Hello, pumpkin. Hello, little baldy bean.
哪儿找到的？这可怜的孩子一个人在荒野里
- Where'd you find it?- The poor kid, all alone in the wild.
几只剑齿虎包围了他
Sabers were closing in on him.
我把他…抢了过来噢，好勇敢
- So I just snatched him.- So brave.
啊，是啊，他需要我我好想也能有一个自己的孩子
Yeah, well, he needed me,and I only wish I had one of my own, too.
是吗？我…我就迷这样的男子
Really? I find that attractive in a male.
唉，谁不想要个家庭呢
Alas. Who wouldn't wanta family, I always say.
噢，真是相见恨晚是啊，这……可不是嘛
- Where've you been hiding?- Yeah, well, you know...
小淘气，嗯？所以，正如我说的，小姐们
Cute kid, huh? So, as I was saying, ladies...
嘿,嗨,曼尼.
Hey. Hi, Manny.
你怎么回事
What's the matter with you?
失陪一下，小姐们，你们在这儿继续泡着，我就回来
Excuse me, ladies. You just keep marinating and I'll be right back.
性感
Sexy.
他长得不怎么样可要找个顾家的太难了
He's not much to look at,but it's so hard to find a family guy.
可不是嘛那些细腻的都被吃光了
Tell me about it.All the sensitive ones get eaten.
不，曼尼，我求你了我需要他
No, no, no. Manny, please,I'm begging you. I need him.
怎么，小帅哥还用泡妞？得了，你别寒碜我了
- A good-looking guy like you?- You say that, but you don't mean it.
不，我当真，瞧瞧你那两个小姐都被你迷晕了
No, seriously. Look at you.Those ladies, they don't stand a chance.
你这幽默感还真刻毒我不想搅你的好事
- You have a cruel sense of humor.- Don't let me cramp your style.
谢谢，曼尼，真够朋友，够哥们别带孩子去
- Thanks, Manny. You're a pal.- Without Pinky.
我需要他
Manny, I need him.
小姐们，说到哪儿了？
So, ladies, where were we?
卡尔镇静，弗兰克
- Carl.- Easy, Frank.
看见漂亮妞，他就象头猎豹至于那老虎
Pretty tail walks by, suddenly he moves like a cheetah. And that tiger...
那“跟踪大师”连树懒都找不到
Yeah, Mr Great Tracker.Can't even find a sloth.
我成什么了？奶妈？你在看什么，小捣蛋？
What am l? The wet nurse?What are you looking at, bone bag?
瞧瞧你，你会长成一个大猛兽
Look at you. You're gonna grow into a great predator.
哼，我看不会，你有什么只有一撮毛
I don't think so. What have you got?You got a little patch of fur.
没有尖牙，没有利爪
No fangs, no claws.
你的皮和肉是那么…软绵绵
You're folds of skin wrapped in mush.
你有什么可怕的？
What's so threatening about you?
嘿，这不是“动物园”里摸小动物
Does this look likea petting zoo to you? Huh?
好吧，耍小聪明？该罚你坐一会儿了
OK. All right, wise guy.You just earned a time-out.
噢，你觉得好玩？那这个呢？
You think that's funny? How about this?
猫头鹰会吃了你
You'll be a little snack for the owls.
你这小鬼还挺勇敢
You're a brave little squirt, I'll give you that.
谢天谢地！谢天谢地！
Thank goodness. Thank goodness.No.
有…老虎！
A tiger.
救命！救命！
Help. Help.
孩子在哪儿？噢，他没事，曼尼带着
- Where's the baby?- Manfred has him.
快“咬”住我快，他咬住我了！
Just put me in your mouth.Come on. Hurry up. He got me.
噢，救命
Help.
你别来烦我他往这边跑了
- Get away from me.- It went this way.
这儿！
Over here.
噢，卡尔！老虎抢先得手
Carl. The tiger beat us to him.
检查一下
Wait a minute.
没错，他的确死了
He's dead all right.
食肉动物就是开心
Carnivores have all the fun.
我也不想那么伤他们的心我是迫不得已
Gosh, I hate breaking their hearts like that. But you know how it is.
好吧，谢谢，可以把我放下了
All right, thanks. You can put me down now.
曼尼,曼尼
Manny. Manny.
我们不是急着赶路吗？迭戈，把他吐出来
Guys, I thought we were in a hurry.And Diego, spit that out.
别弄脏了嘴
You don't know where it's been.
妈呀，刚才有一会儿我还以为你真要吃了我
Boy. For a second there,I thought you were gonna eat me.
我不吃烂杂碎我还以为
- I don't eat junk food.- Thought you were gonna...
我真以为你…你想吗？
I thought you were gonna... Were you?
等等我，慢点，慢点你们能等我一下吗？
Come on, wait up. Wait up. Come on,come on. Can you wait a second, please?
嘿，伙计们
Fellas.
谢谢等我
Thanks for waiting.
3、2、1
Three, two, one...
确实挺“忠诚”
Sure is faithful.
再闹，我就要火了噢，是他引起的
- Don't make me reach back.- He started it.
我不管谁引起的，再闹就罚！
I don't care who started it. I'll finish it.
现代建筑，撑不了多久的
Modern architecture. It'll never last.
嗨哟,曼尼
Hiya, Manny.
嗨，迭戈．
Hi, Diego.
嘿，希德．
Hey, Sid.
你迷路了，对吗？没有，我很清楚我们在哪儿
- You're lost.- No. I know exactly where we are.
让他指指方向
Ask him directions.
我不要他指方向算了，我来问他
- I don't need directions.- Fine, I'll ask him.
嘿，伙计你看见有人类经过吗？
Buddy. You see any humans go by here?
呜,我喜欢猜字,OK
I love this game. I love this game. OK, OK.
三个字,第一个字呃…“跺”,不,“踩”
Three words. First word.Stomp. No, no. Stamp, stamp.
我猜猜,呃…“群”!
Let me try. Pack.
猜得好,曼尼,“一群”长牙…和爪子
Good one, Manny.Pack of long teeth and claws.
一群狼?一群…
Pack of wolves? Pack of...
呃,一群熊!一群跳蚤?
Pack of bears? Pack of fleas?
一群胡须?一群…鼻子?
Pack of whiskers? Pack of noses?
呃…厚皮动物?一群谎言!
- Pachyderm?- Pack of lies.
一群麻烦!一群打手!呃，一群鸟!
Pack of troubles. Pack a wallop.Pack of birds.
一群飞鱼
Pack of flying fish.
嘿!好消息!我找到一条近路!
Great news. I found a shortcut.
什么近路?就是走着要比走长路快
- What do you mean, shortcut?- I mean faster than the long way around.
噢!我知道什么叫“近路”!
I know what a shortcut is.
我们穿过去就能比人类先到“冰川道”不然就会错过他们
Either we beat the humans to Glacier Passor we take the long way and miss 'em.
穿过那儿?你把我当什么了?
Through there? What do you take me for?
明天这个时候你…就可以自由了
This time tomorrow,you could be a free mammoth.
或继续做保姆玩“躲躲猫”我是不会腻的
Or a nanny. I never get tired of peekaboo.
伙计们,瞧这个
Guys. Guys. Check this out.
老虎找到一条近路
Sid, the tiger found a shortcut.
不,谢谢,我想活命
No, thanks. I choose life.
那我建议你最好还是走近路
Then I suggest you take the shortcut.
你在威胁我吗?走,树懒!
- Are you threatening me?- Move, sloth!
好样的,老虎
Way to go, tiger.
快!快进去!
Quick. Get inside.
好吧,那就走近路吧
OK, I vote shortcut.
好了,伙计们,都跟紧些这儿很容易走丢
Guys, stick together.It's easy to get lost in here.
呃…伙计们?
Guys?
啊!小鱼儿
A fish.
你跟上,行不行?看住一个宝宝已经够难的了
Will you keep up, please?Hard enough to keep track of one baby.
我…抓住你了
I gotcha.
船长,前方有冰山!
Captain, iceberg ahead.
哦，不
Oh, no.
谁想玩第二回合?
Yeah. Who's up for round two?
叫…叫…叫孩子小心点
Tell the kid to be more careful.
瞧,瞧,老虎,瞧啊
Look, look. Tigers.
不,没事的,没事的瞧,老虎和羚羊在做游戏
No, it's OK, it's OK. Look, the tigers are just playing tag with the antelope.
捉到摸一下,用牙摸来吧,希德,我们也来玩
- With their teeth.- Come on, Sid, let's play tag.
你捉我
You're it.
行啊…好吧,好吧哪儿画着树懒?
Sure. OK, OK, OK, where are the sloths?
这上面怎么没画树懒?你们注意到吗?
You never see any sloths.Have you ever noticed?
瞧,曼尼,一头毛象噢,我可真兴奋
- Look, Manny, a mammoth.- Somebody pinch me.
嘿,嘿,这头胖的看上去可真象你
Hey, hey, this fat one looks just like you.
噢,他有家庭
And he's got a family.
他很幸福瞧,他在陪孩子玩
And he's happy.Look, he's playing with his kid.
瞧,曼尼,这就是你的问题毛象应该象他们那样
See? That's your problem.That's what mammoths are supposed to do.
找头母象…生一头毛象宝宝
- Find a she-mmoth, have baby mammoths...
希德
- Sid.
干嘛?闭嘴
- What?- Shut up.
可…噢
But...
噢,快瞧啊
Would you look at that.
老虎没带错路这是“半峰山”
The tiger actually did it. There's Half Peak.
下一站,冰川道
Next stop, Glacier Pass.
我真不该怀疑你你听见吗,小家伙?
- How could I ever have doubted you?- Did you hear that, little fella?
你快到家了
You're almost home.
我的脚在冒汗你身体每出现一个反应
- My feet are sweating.- Do we need a news flash
我们都得发布新闻?他要我们注意他
- every time your body does something?- lgnore him.
是真的我的脚真的很烫!噢,噢
Seriously. My feet are really hot.
是你的肚子在叫吧?
Tell me that was your stomach.
嘘,我肯定是那是雷声
I'm sure it was just thunder.
声音…来自…地下?
From underground?
快,跟我一起跑
Come on, keep up with me.
可你原地不动!
I would if you were moving.
哇,但愿我也能跳成全你了!
- I wish I could jump like that.- Wish granted.
快!跑快点!难道你没看到熔岩流吗?
- Come on, move faster.- Have you noticed the river of lava?
抱紧他!
Hold Pinky.
曼尼
Manny.
曼尼,你没事吧?求你说点什么,什么都行
Manny, Manny, Manny, you OK?Come on, come on, say something. Anything.
什么?什么?我听不清
What? What? I can't hear you.
你站在我的鼻子上了
You're standing on my trunk.
啊,你没事!你没事你为什么那么干?
- You're OK. You're OK.- Why did you do that?
你冒死…救了我的命
You could have died, trying to save me.
大家是一个集体
That's what you do in a herd.
得互相照顾
You look out for each other.
噢!谢谢
Well, thanks.
不知你们怎么想,可我觉得我们这“集体”是最怪的
I don't know about you guys,but we are the weirdest herd I've ever seen.
我的爪子都快等不及要撕烂那毛象了!
I can't wait to getmy claws in that mammoth.
谁都不能碰那毛象除非我先得到…孩子!
No one touches the mammoth until I get that baby.
首先,我要把那毛象撕开扯烂
First, I'll slice its hindquarters into sections.
把白色肉放一堆,深色…嘿,别再说了!我饿坏了!
- I'll put the white meat in one pile and...- Knock it off. I'm starving.
肩膀的肉…可能比较老但绝对多汁
Next, the shoulders. Occasionally tough, but extremely juicy.
警告过你了,别再说了!省点力气吧!
- I told you to knock it off.- Save your energy.
要杀毛象谈何容易
Mammoths don't go down easy.
只有一个办法
There's only one way to do it.
首先,得把他逼上死角
First, you have to force it into a corner.
切断他的退路等你们三个把他困住
Cut off its retreat.And when you three have it trapped,
我就咬断他的喉咙
I'll go for the throat.
伙计们,别让孩子吹着风!
Guys, we gotta get this kid outta the wind.
还有多远?三英里
- How much further?- Three miles.
我累坏了,我们早上能到
I'm beat. We'll get there in the morning.
你在干嘛?我让树懒…名垂千古
- What are you doing?- I'm putting sloths on the map.
那得画得现实点画他在睡觉
Why don't you make it realistic and draw him lying down?
画得“圆”一些
And make him rounder.
好极了哈!我真笑不出来
- Perfect.- I forgot how to laugh.
我是个天才
I'm a genius.
从现在起,你们得称呼我“希德-火焰之王”
From now on you'll have torefer to me as Sid, Lord of the Flame.
嘿,火焰之王,你尾巴着火了
Lord of the Flame, your tail's on fire.
噢,谢谢,从现在起我就管你叫…“迭戈”
Thank you. From now on,I'm gonna call you Diego.
“摸我你是死定之王”
Lord of "Touch Me and You're Dead".
我是说着玩的你这没头脑的
I'm just kidding, you little knucklehead.
嘿,小俩口
Lovebirds.
快瞧
Look at this.
这简直……太神了
I don't believe it.
过来,小家伙过来,你这小虫虫
Come here, you little biped.Come here, you little wormy-worm.
到希德叔叔这儿来
Come to Uncle Sid.
这边,这边
No, no... This way. This way.
不,去他那儿
No, no, no. No, go to him.
去他那儿
Go to him.
好吧
OK.
干得好,接着…练习吧
Good job. Keep practicing.
快瞧啊,我们的小家伙在长大
Look at that. Our little guy is growing up.
好了,过来该睡了,肉团儿
All right, come on. Sleep time, lumpy.
他对孩子就是亲
Look at that big pushover.
要知道,迭戈我还没有能冒死救我的朋友呢
You know, Diego, I've never hada friend who would risk his life for me.
是啊,曼尼他…他真好
Yeah, Manny's... he's a good guy.
是啊,的确
Yeah, he is.
好了,晚安
Well, good night.
让我给你弄干净,你这么又脏又臭的回去,你老爸会怎么说?
Let's get you all cleaned up. What's your daddy gonna say if you go back all stinky?
我来擦干净,嗯,好多了这儿还有点儿
Let me just clean that up.That looks good. A little bit here.
擦干净真漂亮,小家伙他长得越来越象我了
- You clean up nice, little fella.- I think he's starting to look like me.
嘿,迭戈,你说呢?
Diego, what do you think?
也许不该送回去为什么?
- Maybe we shouldn't do this.- Why not?
因为他长大后会成为猎人你说他会猎杀谁?
If we save him, he'll be a hunter.And who do you think he'll hunt?
也许救了他他就不会成猎人
Maybe because we save him,he won't hunt us.
是啊,也许他会长出毛和长脖然叫你“妈妈”
Yeah, and maybe he'll grow fur anda long skinny neck and call you Mama.
你怎么回事?没什么,我们走,冻死我了
- What's your problem?- Nothing. Let's go. I'm freezing my tail off.
嘿,迭戈,你被冻住了吗?
Diego. You frozen back there?
低下身子!什么?
- Get down.- What?
嘘,低下身跟我走嘿,怎么回事?
- Get down and follow me.- What's going on?
在半峰山脚下有个埋伏…等着你们
At the bottom of Half Peak,there's an ambush waiting for you.
什么?你说什么“埋伏”?
- What?- What do you mean, "ambush"?
你设了圈套!那是我的任务!
- You set us up.- It was my job.
我得把孩子抢到手,可是你把我们带回家当晚餐
- I was to get the baby, but then...- You brought us home for dinner.
行了!你被开除了!真对不起
- That's it. You're out of the herd.- I'm sorry.
我宰了你…你再后悔吧
No, you're not. Not yet.
听着,我能帮你们跟紧了,希德,我们能杀出去!
- Listen, I can help you.- Stay close, Sid. We can fight our way out.
不行!他们太强大了你们得信任我
You can't. The pack's too strong.You have to trust me.
信任你?我们干嘛要信任你?
Trust you? Why in the world would we trust you?
因为你们只有靠我
Because I'm your only chance.
哈罗,“小姐”们
Hello, ladies.
嘿,瞧谁终于肯露脸了迭戈,我正为你担心呢
- Look who decided to show up.- Diego, I was beginning to worry about you.
用不着担心,再过两分钟你将从…复仇中…得到满足
No need to worry. In about two minutesyou'll be satisfying your taste for revenge.
这非常好
Very nice.
我看见树懒了!孩子在他手里!
I see the sloth. And he's got the baby.
没见到毛象就别暴露你们自己我们得出其不意
Don't give away your positions until yousee the mammoth. He's the one to surprise.
你想重拳出击对吗,齐克?
You want to maul something, don't you?
呵呵,我想出击那你还等什么?
- I wanna maul.- Then what are you waiting for?
不,我说了等那毛象出现!
No, I said wait for the mammoth.
“雪板挠背”你们吃白雪吧!嘿嘿
Backscratcher. Eat my powder!
唷!喔!“环滑车”呃,啊!
Loop-de-loop.
障碍滑雪,障碍滑雪，宝贝
Slalom! Slalom, baby!
对不起,伙计们他被冻成小雪人了
Sorry, fellas. He got a little frostbite.
呜!宰了他!
Get him.
大惊喜!
Surprise!
好吧,跟我来!我们去找希德,然后离开这儿
OK, follow me. We'll pick up Sidand get outta here while we can.
来吧,迭戈我们把这毛象摆平
Come on, Diego,let's bring this mammoth down.
他在这儿
There he is.
没错,宝宝在哪儿啊?
That's right. Where's the baby?
这就叫…适者…生存!
Survival of the fittest.
这老虎不行
I don't think so. Yeah.
你这是干嘛?不许…碰这…毛象
- What are you doing?- Leave the mammoth alone.
好,我先把你摆平
Fine. I'll take you down first.
我们赢了
We did it.
我们曾经是多棒的集体
We were some team, huh?
曾经是?胡说,我们还是一个集体
Were? Come on, we're still a team.
我设下圈套,真对不起
I'm sorry I set you up.
我就算恨你,也懒得记仇了
You know me -I'm too lazy to hold a grudge.
嘿,别闹,小鬼
Knock it off, squirt.
你得强壮些
You gotta be strong.
你得照顾曼福雷德和希德
You have to take care of Manfred and Sid.
尤其是希德
Especially Sid.
行了,你能挺过来,你是老虎
Come on, you can lick this. You're a tiger.
我能背你,你说怎么样?
Look, I'll carry you.Come on, what do you say?
振作点,迭戈,振作!
Come on, Diego, come on.
告诉他他会好的,曼尼
Tell him he's going to be OK, Manny.
听着,你们别管我了
Listen, you have to leave me here.
如果人类过了“冰川道”你们就找不到他们了
If those humans get through the pass,you'll never catch them.
你不用救我的
You didn't have to do that.
我们是一个集体
That's what you do in a herd.
别忘了我们
Don't forget about us.
好吗?
OK?
我们不会忘了你
We won't forget about you.
再见,再见
Goodbye.
Goodbye.Goodbye.
希德再见
- Sid...- Bye.
再见
Bye.
对,对,没错宝宝在哪儿
That's right. Where's the baby?
走吧,希德,我们去南方
Come on, Sid, let's head south.
再见
Bye.
省口气吧,希德人类不会说话
Save your breath, Sid.You know humans can't talk.
迭戈?你没事!
Diego? You're OK.
我有九条命呢
- Nine lives, baby.- You're OK.
你没事!
You're OK.
我亲亲你!呀!呜
I could kiss ya.
欢迎回来,搭挡,要我背吗?
Welcome back, partner. Wanna lift?
不,谢谢我得保住仅存的那点尊严
No thanks. I gotta save whatever dignity I've got left.
你跟我们混在一块了就别管什么尊严了吧,就背我吧
You're hanging out with us. Dignity'sgot nothing to do with it. I'll take that lift.
好,爬上来吧托我一把,咿哈
- Yeah, climb aboard.- Pick me up, buddy.
或者不说“驾”,随你喜欢
Mush. Or not mush. Either way.
这将是我最棒的一次迁徙
This is gonna be the best migration ever.
我带你们去我的宝地,我毛里的真菌干死后我会变成棕色
I'll show you my favorite watering holes.I turn brown when the fungus in my fur dries.
这真有意思我说,这“冰川时代”可真没劲
- Attractive.- This whole lce age thing is getting old.
知道我喜欢什么“全球变暖”
You know what I could go for?Global warming.
做梦去吧我可是说真的
- Keep dreaming.- No, really...
两万年以后
20,000 Years Later
谢谢观看!